Kaiyu Hou

(+1) 847-641-0586 <u>kaiyuhou2022@u.northwestern.edu</u> <u>www.kyhou.com</u>

I am currently a 4th year Ph.D. candidate in the Computer Science Department at Northwestern University, advised by Prof. Yan Chen. I have a broad interest in various aspects of cloud networks and network protocols. My current research focuses on network optimization of microservices/serverless based cloud. I am also working for introducing formal methods into network protocol verification.

Education

• Ph.D. Student in Computer Science

2017 - (2022)

Northwestern University

Evanston, IL

- Advisor: Prof. Yan Chen Area: Network Protocols, Cloud Networking GPA: 3.97/4.00

• Master's in Computer Science

2014 - 2017

Xi'an Jiaotong University

Shaanxi, China

- Advisor: Prof. Chengchen Hu Area: SDN Rank: 1st/89 GPA: 3.81/4.00 Average: 91.7

• B.E. in Software Engineering Xi'an Jiaotong University

2010 - 2014

Shaanxi, China

- Rank: 1st/78 GPA: 3.94/4.00 Average: 92.4 (in Junior and Senior years)

Work Experiences

• SRI International

Menlo Park, CA

Research Intern, at Computer Science Laboratory,

Jun. 2020 - Sep. 2020

- Designed and implemented an enterprise-wide radio situational awareness system
- Passively collected radio traffics, including Wi-Fi and Bluetooth, analyzed by deep learning

Research: Cloud Networks & SDN

• Network Optimizing for Microservices/Serverless Cloud (work in progress)

2020 - Present

- Microservices/Serverless architectures bring flexibility but introduce network communication delay
- Designed systematic metrics to provide a benchmark for the microservices network performance
- Integrated QUIC into **OpenFaaS/Kubernetes** to improve serverless network performance

• Generic Security Policy Enforcement System for SDN-based Cloud

2017 - 2018

- Designed a **policy language** for resource protection and management of SDN-based Cloud
- Implemented in the **OpenDaylight** controller, and deployed on **OpenStack**

• Routing Policy for Solving Reactive Model Overhead of SDN

2016 - 2017

- Proposed a routing policy to reduce the control channel bandwidth consumption up to 80%
- Implemented in the Floodlight controller under the OpenFlow protocol with Open vSwitch
- Deployed on the ONetSwitch, an OpenFlow/P4 white-box switch with Xilinx FPGA

Research: Formal Methods for Network Protocols

• Formal Verification and Vulnerability Detection of LTE/5G Protocols

2019 - 2020

- Used **TLA+** to formally specify the emergency call systems in **4G/5G** cellular network protocols
- Built a **complete cellular network testbed** (USRP, OpenAirInterface) for real-world verification
- Discovered serious availability and security issues in real world, acknowledged by major carriers

- 2020 2021
- Traditionally, researchers use secure properties to verify a protocol is safe or find counterexamples
- We convert this decision problem into a search problem. Given the model and the properties, we aim to search the boundaries of the configuration space where the system is always secure and reliable

Selected Publications

- You Li*, Kaiyu Hou*, Yan Chen, Hai Zhou (*equal contribution), Property Guided Secure Configuration
 Space Search, Under Review, CAV'21
- Kaiyu Hou*, You Li*, Yinbo Yu, Yan Chen, Hai Zhou (*equal contribution), Discovering Emergency Call
 Pitfalls for Cellular Networks with Formal Methods, Under Review, MobiSys'21
- You Li*, Kaiyu Hou*, Hai Zhou, Yan Chen (*equal contribution), Network Protocol Safe Configuration Search in One Shot, SIGCOMM'20, Poster
- Xiaochun Wu, Kaiyu Hou, Xue Leng, Xing Li, Yinbo Yu, Bo Wu, Yan Chen, State of the Art and Research Challenges in the Security Technologies of Network Function Virtualization, Internet Computing, 2020
- Yinbo Yu, You Li, Kaiyu Hou, Yan Chen, Hai Zhou, Jianfeng Yang, CellScope: Automatically Specifying and Verifying Cellular Network Protocols, SIGCOMM'19, Poster
- Xue Leng, Kaiyu Hou, Yan Chen, Kai Bu, Libin Song, SDNKeeper: Lightweight Resource Protection and Management System for SDN-based Cloud, IWQoS'18
- Chengchen Hu, **Kaiyu Hou** (1st student author), Hao Li, Ruilong Wang, Peng Zheng, Peng Zhang, Huanzhao Wang, **SoftRing: Taming the Reactive Model for Software Defined Networks**, ICNP'17
- Xiuwen Sun, Kaiyu Hou, Hao Li, Chengchen Hu, Towards A Fast Packet Inspection over Compressed HTTP Traffic, IWQoS'17

Awards & Honor

•	Best Teaching Assistant Award, Northwestern University		2020
•	Outstanding Graduate Award, Xi'an Jiaotong University	2014	, 2017
•	Excellent Student Award, Xi'an Jiaotong University	2011, 2012, 2013, 2015	5, 2016
•	Google Excellence Scholarship, Awarded to 3 students from each of 20	top Chinese universities	2013
•	Meritorious Winner, Mathematical Contest in Modeling (MCM)		2013
•	Silver Medal, ACM-ICPC China Province Contest	2012	2, 2013

Activities & Experiences

- Reviewer/Sub-reviewer of CCS (18', 19'), ICDCS ('18), IEEE ToN
- Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University
 - CS 212: Discrete Mathematics (Rating: 5.1/6.0), CS 214: Data Structures (Rating: 5.3/6.0)
 - CS 340: Introduction to Networking (Rating: 5.4/6.0)
- **Student President of Computer Science Dept**. (Class 2017), Xi'an Jiaotong University 2014 2017
- Chair, the ACM-ICPC Club, Xi'an Jiaotong University 2012 2013

Skills

- Serverless Platforms, Microservices Networks, Cloud Networks, SDN | Python, Go-lang
- L2/L3/L4, 3GPP, 802.11, and QUIC Protocols | Formal Methods for Network Protocols